[Music]
hello welcome to voice guard my name is
Tim Adeline and this is a conversation
with David fuller hope you enjoy
[Music]
so now the tables are turned instead
instead of doing the interview I'm going
to use yeah all I really know ten is
that you contacted me and said you feel
a real alignment with what you're doing
and what we're doing and would like an
interview so tell me more well means
it's clear that well perhaps this really
should begin with me asking you what
rebel wisdoms about I mean to get at the
alignment I'd have to tell you what I'm
doing and then that might take a little
bit of time but fundamentally I see you
attempting gap conversations with
interesting and important people as they
appear out of the haze on the world
stage at the moment and you know I'm
interested in who you are and why you're
doing that and perhaps ultimately what
the personal drive is that finds you in
the position you are I guess the simple
answer is that I feel that's what I
meant to be doing I've got a set of
skills from being a journalist and a
documentary maker for a long time I
never felt like a complete fit with
partly the mainstream media and partly
just TV as a medium it didn't really
seem to go deep enough and since I've
started making stuff for YouTube I kind
of realized that one there's an appetite
for real intellectual content again
which is great and also that I've got
something to offer and I think what I
have to offer is I see how things fit
together like I see who when I when I
saw Jordan Peterson last year I knew
straight away that this was the key
message that we needed to integrate as a
culture it's like materialism is
breaking down a lot of the structures
are breaking down under the force of
like the Deconstructor force of the
internet and there's there's a kind of
sense that this is the time for new
ideas and I think white people are
really hungry for new ideas is because
we all sense certainly with the election
of trumpets like the idea the adults are
in charge in any kind of meaningful way
is is obviously not true and I think we
all kind of sense that something yeah on
some deep level a lot of the ideas that
the running Western society for quite a
while are breaking down and I think that
is yeah it's the end of materialism it's
the end of the kind of the
rational intellect that questions
everything or questions everything until
it can't question anything else I mean
that's kind of post-modernism in a way
and what we need is a reintegration of
the sacred the archetypal the
mythological the irrational for want of
a better word and that's what I see in
Peterson and that's what I see I think
rebel wisdom I think is a conversation
they say that every great newspaper is a
conversation so it may not agree all the
time or there may be different
perspectives say like a great newspaper
will have different perspectives but it
will have a certain overall tone and the
overall tone of rebel wisdom is what are
the ideas what are the practices what
are the kind of embodied forms of
knowledge that we need to get through
what I think are going to be a pretty
chaotic next 10 years or so and so we're
we're doing stuff about psychedelics
because I think that's a really
important kind of opening up to the
beyond that the numinous that kind of
we're also doing workshops because I
think you can do the film you can make
films and I think we are making like
really interesting films interesting
interviews but ultimately you have to if
you want to put an idea into practice
you have to build that into your life
and you have to question your beliefs
you have to question your conditioning
the way you were brought up sort of all
the ways that you hold yourself back and
I think all of that like I think the
next 10 years are gonna challenge us all
on every level what we thought was true
we're realizing is not true kind of that
that's still a kind of intellectual
concept but I think a lot of its also
gonna really test our emotional
resilience but the chaos of the times is
gonna it's already happening with social
media like anxiety and depression and
all of these things are growing usually
because we're overwhelmed and we're
being overwhelmed by the world and
that's gonna keep happening I think even
just on in my particular area of
expertise I guess is foreign foreign
affairs and I look around the world my
see five or six flash points that are
likely to explode and likely to kind of
yeah even even that let alone kind of AI
and all the other kind of
essential threats I think we're yeah I
think we're in for a really rocky time
yeah and I also think that if you look
at the intellectual diet web for example
that kind of it's a loose it's a loose
kind of name for a loose movement but I
think as a what I sense the movement is
is a is a coming to consciousness of
these kind of conversations you look at
you look at say the Weinstein brothers
on Dave Rubin that they're raising the
biggest questions and looking for the
biggest answers and that that I think
rebel wisdom is part of that
conversation already we're and we're
trying to we're trying to to be part of
that conversation to push it forward and
to also bring the parts of that
conversation that aren't being had
because there's still a danger but just
be an intellectual conversation like the
intellectual dialogue it's it's an
intellectual conversation actually I
think we need a much deeper resolution
of that sort of an integrating so we've
got interviews with the likes of Stan
Grof stomachs laugh Groff who was the
sort of pioneer of psychedelic therapy
in the 1950s and 1960s
Richard tarnis who was with Stan Grof as
a philosopher in residence at Esalen who
I think wrote the best book about the
history of Western culture and where
we're going called the passion of the
Western mind interesting and so we're
looking for who are the thinkers and
like we have that into group of
Sheldrake which i think is one of our
sort of most popular things so we're
looking at saying okay here are the
thinkers just outside the mainstream of
Western thought who probably have the
answers like they've never been accepted
into the kind of the grand current of
Western thought or Western culture but
they're holding these really important
pieces and I'd add to Jamie wheal too
that was a kind of who's a modern day
flow expert like he he's holding a
really key piece so I'm looking around
and seeing how the pieces fit together
and say ok he's got an important piece
this person got an important piece
she's got an important piece I mean
everything there is but Louise Mazzanti
for example who's appeared in a few of
our films so far I think is is an
incredible force and is is again holding
a really important piece of the puzzle
we've got a powerful presence in her
doubt about that yeah and I hope that in
a year's time lots of the people that we
featured have a much higher profile that
in the same way that we put out the
piece about Jordan Peterson and then he
he reached this sort of new audience
simultaneously I'm not saying that we
were in any way responsible for that was
about a million factors yeah I'm a total
course I'm not I'm not saying that that
I am saying I knew that that would
happen nothing the first question I
asked him during my interview was one
what do you make of what's been going on
and two are you ready for it to keep
going mmm because I knew that it was he
was on this exponential curve and
there's a yeah I really that named the
exponential curve I think really sums up
what we're doing I think we're on that
same exponential curve and the
exponential curve so what the what the
Internet allows is to sort of crowd
source than assess the necessary answers
and the necessary information for this
time mm-hmm and that's so Jordan
Peterson was basically crowdsource the
intellectual diet was kind of
crowdsource they were forced together
like Dave Rubin talks about this was
meant to happen because they were so
popular they were being forced on to
each other shows by their audience hey
get Sam Harris on get Joe Rogan on so
there's a real the Internet has allowed
this sort of self-generated conversation
to emerge and it's just in time I think
and the fact that it's emerging shows
that everything is quite fragile like
it's it's being summoned on some sort of
archetypal level that we need the
answers we need are being summoned by
the internet and crowd-sourced as we
need them and I think that's that gives
me hope that it also also pretty much
all of the kind of the best thinkers I
know are quite pessimistic about our
prospects for the next 10 years or so
like we we're still acting like tribal
beings in a world where tribalism is no
longer an option for example right yeah
well no that was brilliant I mean it's
so much there so at one level it's about
what are those idea
that are built for storms and how do you
properly talk about them and integrate
them when the time comes but the time is
always now because there is always
responsibility you can take for whether
it's integrating something difficult or
looking to that place where you're
vulnerable and trying to speak to that
and apply in a way that's practical and
health oriented for your life so you
mentioned in Jordan Peterson and you
also mentioned an exponential curve I'd
be interested in the shape you see that
curve taking now obviously it's a curve
upwards one would hope but there's an
interesting idea that comes out of many
mystical ways of thinking and also out
of Stan Groff's work and our chemical
ideas and and many other ways but it's
just generally this idea of cycles of
transformation or deaths and rebirths
and you can consider them metaphorically
or we could get metaphysical about it
but at the metaphorical level applying
that to the idea of this upward curve it
means there are going to be you know
troughs and and then Peaks again almost
as if if you're moving towards a vision
and and you're at the top of a mountain
you're looking over another and you see
a land beyond it to actually get to that
land you have to go down the mountain
first and then you can't quite see where
you're going and and you're into the
darkness again but then up again right
and so you talk about the J curve like
things have to get worse before they get
better right and what do you think we
are my friend I think we I think we're
on the downward curve and my friend Nick
jankle talks about the J curve because
if you're if you're sort of say you're
kind of things are going ok in order for
them to get better you have to destroy
the things that are just about okay like
you're coping like it think about in
your own life your coping strategies
your ego structures your way of dealing
with things often you'll reach a crisis
where those don't work anymore and the
ultimate solution is that you're you'll
come out of it and you'll you'll be in a
healthier space you'll find some ways of
kind of yeah some of those believe some
of those habits and they long serving
you but to get to that place you have to
go down into it and I think we're
heading down into it the line
I don't think I think the election of
Trump was the for me at least the kind
of harbinger of of that sense of okay
this is the time it was something yeah
yeah it's kind of okay this is the time
where things like he's whether you
support him or not and I know that we've
got some some people who view our videos
who do support him I I think supporting
or not it's kind of a fairly narrow way
of looking at it I see him as essential
like he's a kind of he's a symptom with
a cause and he's a symptom of a lot of
failure in the system over an awfully
long time and he I mean even just from a
sort of practical level but he's ripping
up all of the international agreements
he's ripping up the entire kind of world
order that was set up after the second
world war by people who went through the
Second World War and realized how bad
things could get right and what we have
now 70 years on is we've lost all the
life experience of people who went
through that so I suspect we're going to
go through something similar hmm yes
ibly yeah I think we'll go through
something similar in the next sort of 10
years or so and in terms of sort of the
exponential curve and what it looks like
I think it looks a bit like BitTorrent
so BitTorrent is you have you start off
with one one central node which has all
the information and then it propagates
out to everyone but then from everyone
to everyone at the same time yep so I
think that's kind of how it works right
and what's important is actually what is
the process or movement that is most
adaptive for that well that for the
individuals who are then the the next
nodes sprung out from the first node and
how how in their own development do they
relate to the adaptive movement of that
initial node then we could tie this in
together actually with what you just
mentioned about Trump because for sure
he's a symptom but he's also an
individual and a powerful individual and
is a course in his own right and I think
the thing about Trump is that you can
make arguments for his necessity and
current systemic place we're in but at
the same time it's it's immediately
apparent for most people what his
individual flaws are and and how he is
yeah I mean perhaps not in control of
what he could be you know as much as you
might imagine an integrated individual
to be so something I'm particularly
interested in is how is how the cycle
plays out in an individual life and
there's also a way to tie rationality
and this other kind of mystical way into
this as well I mean one way you can
think about mysticism is out is as a way
of seeing right is as the place from
from where it Givens emerge right but
they may or may not be adaptive for the
current framework we're all in so you
have to apply analysis and rationality
to work out what's going on in there but
fundamentally you have to empty that out
again and then to resubmit
back into that domain that enables the
the the seeing of novelty from wherever
you are I mean there's a lots of ways to
explore those ideas in a more articulate
way but I do see that interplay as being
particularly involved in what we see
Jordan Peterson do you know he's someone
to me that is he's a he's a creative
thinker first and foremost but he's also
a obviously a scientist you know and
well he's he's capable of pissing off
just about anyone because he has
developed quite an idiosyncratic way of
thinking even though it's got a lineage
it has a real lineage and perhaps
perhaps one of the things he's done
that's most novel is sought in sort of a
stack on top of one another many levels
of analysis that attempt to represent
the same pattern but nevertheless it's
Reap articular izing these fundamental
ideas to terminology that works for him
is a creative act itself which it
depends how deep you ultimately think
our creativity can go if we're just left
with three particular izing some
ultimately really fundamental like some
sort of cycle of death and rebirth we
could talk about that a number of ways
or can we transcend to some domain a
real radical novelty that's even it
quite impossible to comprehend but
anyway where we might take all of that
is what is the right way to integrate
even a conversation about that right and
for me it's one that is based on on
honesty fundamentally and and you can
and what I see in what you're trying to
do with rebel wisdom is to approach
difficult conversations with honesty
that's really number one so there's I
suppose another element to this as well
which is taking from the online sphere
which is where the communication happens
on the mass level but also actually
properly setting that up in in real life
face-to-face life so I wonder about your
vision for events in the future and and
how it can work for people to be
properly involved is the audience like
how much audience interaction should
there be should people be spitting off
and having conversations in smaller
groups obviously it's important we see
to you know a couple people at the front
talking to each other but fundamentally
people have to engage themselves like
like you say so what is the appropriate
spiraling noddle like structure that
best gets people to be involved in this
creative transformative process I don't
know the answer to that question really
no and I think with our next podcast
we're going to inaugurate a discussion
group or something on Facebook mm-hmm we
I don't know what the format is I think
partly we have to facilitate in person
discussions because broadcast is not
good enough to to be able to provide the
context and the kind of body language
the kind of receptivity that there's
what happened to have cele dialogue with
each other but I think yeah I think it's
going to have to be continually
decentralized there can be its own
holding the balance between
decentralization but not chaos
and at the moment at the moment what
decentralized and often means is sort of
a value what it comes with is a value
system of relativity right so or
relativism rather right so how do you
reintroduce and this is do you know
spiral dynamics there's called Ken
Wilber idea I probably am familiar with
the concepts but you might have quite
useful map because he talks about green
consciousness being postmodern
relativistic it's the sort of dominant
form of consciousness on the planet at
the moment and and the crisis we're
seeing is because it's basically eating
its own tail
it's a necessary step to kind of
relativize absolutist claims and realize
that there is a sort of there are there
are other perspectives and it's valuable
to consider other perspectives but
ultimately if you don't have a
transcendental truth value within it
then you just end up kind of in in the
chaos that we're seeing at the moment
yeah man we see a post truth world so he
talks about integral thinking being the
level above green an integral thinking
reintroduces hierarchy it reintroduces
it reintroduces truth that reintroduces
hierarchy and it reintroduces yeah it
bypasses a lot of the pathologies of the
previous stages and i thought i thought
i mean it's it's only a map but it's
quite a useful map I think and I'd
really recommend there's a book called
Trump in the post truth world which Ken
Wilber wrote after the election of Trump
that's really good because it it applies
this what can be quite esoteric
theorizing is integral theory to real
world events and it really explains
what's going on basically Green
relativism identity politics stopped
functioning as a leading edge so what
happens is we've rebooted to a kind of
earlier stage of tribalism and that's
what Trump represents that's what breaks
that represents and it's a necessary
thing to happen because this these sort
of so-called liberal elites were
basically going off on their own
direction and secretly hating all of the
people that didn't think the same as
them so this is kind of ideology of
openness
we're so open to all of these different
kind of ideas and perspectives and races
and genders and sexualities apart from
those people who don't think like after
these traditionalists who have
different attitudes towards a gay
marriage or whatever their bigoted and
racist and homophobic and we do so this
this sort of there was this hidden
shadow of liberal superiority and hate
that lots of people picked up on
especially I mean obviously brexit as an
example in the UK and Trump as an
example in in America where in the UK
for example they're quite valid concerns
about uncontrolled immigration are seen
by the liberal by the sort of liberal
left as racist and bigoted and they're
the and they're generally these people
don't live in the areas that are really
affected by these by this immigration
yeah and so what you had is in with
Breck's and with Trump they were given a
button marked you and enough people
pressed oh they press a button yesterday
and I don't blame them for it it's
likely exactly and I think it's a crisis
of Western culture to crisis of the UK
and a crisis of America to say you can't
allow your your country to get too far
ahead of itself if you kind of see it as
sort of more or less of all than I think
I I don't particularly but it's like if
the divisions get too broad you have to
stop and come back together and I think
there's a healing that needs to happen
in both the UK and the u.s. that at the
moment I don't see happening because the
Liberals seem to have doubled down on
their Wow
Trump got elected the country is it's
far worse than we thought it's far
racing more racist than we thought far
more homophone and slightly look look at
what's really happening look at the
reception of someone like milo who
openly gay talks about his black
boyfriend got in rural america these are
not these are not just the sort of I'm
sure there are racist and homophobic
people there but this is not what's
going on
and this liberal what I fear is that
we're actually we're actually seeing its
spiral further rather than this sort of
healing that needs to happen and I my
belief is that it might be possible to
have these this is what the intellectual
dialogue is about as well as hope there
are certain conversations that we need
to
and they're being stopped at the moment
by this ideology the conversations about
gender differences for example are being
stopped because of this ideology that
says you can't talk about that or that
it's it's even it's sexist to even
discuss it and there's all of these sort
of third-rail issues within our culture
that that this worldview is stopping us
discussing and the intellectual diet
will be sort of this first
crystallization of this is the cut these
are the conversations we need to have
have because you can't talk about
inequality if you don't recognize the
fact that we are not equal in some areas
to start with absolutely so that
conversation needs to be had I suspect
that that conversation can be had in the
UK and I don't think it can be had in
the u.s. yeah I know it's too polarized
they're too reactive the culture wars
are too entrenched there's a kind of
civility in the UK but and politeness
that I think work could allow us to
reach this kind of synthesis and the
UK's talent is for synthesis music
fashion comedy we created the Beatles we
create a Monty Python we create these
sort of the synthesized kind of
movements the u.s. takes them a
polarisers and it's kind of like the
process of but they have the most
forward-thinking and highly evolved say
masters of flow or psychedelics or any
of these things in the world but they
also have some of the most miserable
some of the most drug-addicted some of
our suicide or some of the most
miserable people on the planet and
that's no that's kind of no coincidence
and it's unsustainable and I think
America is in the process of ripping
itself apart because of that it's like
you as a society did not take it's like
Peterson talks about the profit comes
along and says you've not been taking
care of the women and children it's the
same it's like you've not been taking
care of your society you've pretty much
decided that they're nothing to do with
you and that's that is not allowed you
you're not allowed to do that as a
society and remand for it to remain
functional yeah you create you create
too much
resentment and it will grow to the point
that it will take you down yeah well I
mean look there's there's a lot in there
that I think is it's quite persuasive I
mean the message is one that is quite
quite doom-laden there's no doubt about
that you know I mean it just what do you
mean by by the the US isn't going to be
able to properly find that harmony
before this time of real thing if you
look at my friend Jordan green hall
talks about this if you look at the the
language that's being used it's already
one step below actual violence the kind
of the way that people are talking
treason No Surrender like we are already
vulcanized to the point where it looks
unlikely that we will be able to I can
just look at American I can see loads of
different like just imagine a race riot
in American city and Donald Trump sends
in the National Guard
I could easily happen no I can see I can
see an infinite number of potential
flash points in America and I don't see
I don't see where the checks and
balances are to stop that happening I
mean that politics is barely functional
and the whole the whole society seems a
lot more Hollow than I think even it
realizes there's a great film by the guy
who did the wire David Simon is the main
interviewee and kind of created the main
thesis with this film called the house I
live in and it's a very persuasive film
that looks at the drug conflict and
America is the drug war is a kind of
lens to look at the society but that
what it sketches out is a society that's
basically been following because the
same crisis of materialism following
these targets something that Adam Curtis
talked talks about a bit in his films as
well you if you keep pursuing targets
for the sake of targets people learn to
kind of deep the stats but not to
actually do their jobs and so what you
have is a society that's not doing it
for itself it's doing it for for the
yeah it's it's
it's meeting the the targets without
actually doing like a policeman is not
doing his job because he wants to bring
yeah from the best part of himself he
wants to serve his country what's the
service Society in the end even if it
gets into it for that he ends up busting
people on the street corners because
he'll it's much quicker to to get his
stats so what you end up is hollowing
out of society and I think America's
kind of there already it's an outdated
image in other words the people are
aspiring to something aspiring to
something that doesn't actually properly
map on to to what the the adaptive way
of being whatever it is is in the
current world well it's sort of yeah
they've I think they've sacrificed truth
at a fairly fundamental level
and you can't sacrifice truth in the
society and expect to get away with it
mm-hmm so yeah on the on the quite
reasonable assumption that the u.s.
continuing to deteriorate to a point of
utter chaos is a very very very bad
thing well that's not in a way that the
Association of good and bad is part of
the problem well okay okay but you know
we are at this point where a scale so
scary weapons is suck everything it is
of course it's scary but it also depends
what we mean by chaos and one person's
chaos is is going to be a grain of sand
in comparison to someone else's and
we're so powerful that it's it is well
by the nature of chaos impossible really
to fix exactly what we're talking about
here so it's scary we might want to
avoid it as long as that's not papering
over cracks that might mean ways to
properly navigate conflict and now in in
a conversation as a attempting to
grapple with themes that are so
pervasive transpersonal ultimately I'm a
bit out of my depth but I can't say that
in times when I've been able to bridge
otherwise insurmountable conflict love
Beneke mhm and that's a very very well
in one sense is a cliched thing to say
but at other times it can appear like
the most salient and most real thing to
say there is when you want psychedelic
for example when you're on psychedelics
for example but but but also I think
actually more more repeatedly you know
in a romantic relationship or in a
familiar or relationship or in a you
know in a friendship you know I mean it
it's a lot for the potential of what
could be at the same time as also
allowing a sort of relaxing into a
satisfaction somehow with the present
despite what moments before was
suffering I mean so love is a bridge
maker of sorts but there's a as a great
Leonard Cohen line every heart to love
will come but like a refugee and I think
that's where we're going like people
will find it but they'll find it it will
be a struggle to go there mmm well of
course but you can struggle towards it
right now you can run to it right now
yeah I mean thanks to partly you can you
can steer into the skid
in a way you can you can do the work of
you can choose to do the work before
life does it to you well absolutely
anomie and in its in choosing to do the
work it is also life doing it to you at
the same time I mean the the fundamental
existential predicament we're in is is
there today it's there tomorrow the
suffering is there it's there for you to
bear your futility you are your your
ignorance your vulnerability you know
the necessary self-indulgence it takes
to step out and say anything that might
be true about the world but it's a
positive form of self-indulgence you
know it has to be made it's it's all
there all the vulnerabilities there but
it's it's what it's being in some
effectively open state that enables a
proper being with
the suffering and not and not not
immediately recoiling from it at the
same time but about feeling it somehow
so I don't know I'm certainly not in no
position to say to make any prediction
about the world whatsoever whether it be
optimistic or pessimistic I think
fundamentally I mean I'm an optimist and
I would also argue that fundamentally
Jordan Peterson's an optimist as well
and you know that well I well I mean of
course all I mean I will argue for it
though and the reason I will say that is
because now maybe you're right the
reason I will say that is because to be
an optimist really in in the good sense
of it you have to be absolutely
cognizant of the very things to be
pessimistic about and the reality is if
you're stepping forward and living if
you're moving towards the kingdom of God
on the hill which is what is the closest
metaphor I think you'll get well that
we've currently got that gets at what
Jordan Peterson means by his
relationship to God it is about
affirming life in that place of
suffering is what Dostoyevsky said or
Viktor Viktor Frankl quoting Dostoyevsky
is saying you know the thing I fear most
is not to be worthy of my sufferings all
right there's a meaning in suffering but
it but it's a real meaning it's not a
suffering meaning right there's ground
to stand on at the bottom there is
destruction but there's something there
right and it's it's an effective will to
life so on the way that on the way that
I you know the ideas I find most
compelling and my own research and
writing I think the will to life is a is
a as good a final or grounding
metaphysical principle as any and I
think you know I think the reason why
Jordan Peterson's currently maintaining
that even people who profess to be
atheists are in fact religious if they
uphold the judeo-christian morality is
fundamentally because in their movement
in there in there in there being they
are affirming life and that to me is an
optimistic take right the choice to live
is an optimistic take so you might think
that for me I think the beginning place
for philosophy is should I live and we
do have a choice
it seems to me and I will argue for a
genuine choice
despite I very much closed boundaries
and limits on our choice but it is that
it's it's and it's not a rational
principle you know it's an affirmation
it's it's a it's an affectation and the
rationality immediately has to come next
anyway I see them all as part of the
same process you if there's anything
that I've done that is remotely helpful
that it's a real stretch it will be
merely put in this metaphor forward for
the destruction building it into
something better presumably but it's the
metaphor of a waterwheel ok it's all one
it's all one system it's all one process
it's a process philosophical position so
you can't take the wheel out the water
and you'll have destroyed what it is so
the waters the wheels in the stream ok
and as the plank ask things or whatever
come down there and they're picking up
that water that's the land of the
imagination right that's where novelty
emerges from this place of Givens as
they as the water is bared up the part
making begins hole making and part
making I call it that's the analysis
that's the rationality it's necessary
for the whole structure it up turns its
its water makes another stream you can
imagine water wheels in there and it's
links up with the idea of nodes as well
what's the appropriate way to actually
empty yourself of the water while
maintaining the harmony of the structure
itself and again once once your empty
little not to like that some ideas of
Buddhism in there as well you can then
re-enter the water but fundamentally the
movement comes from the hitting of the
stream and the submersion of the plank
casks there and for me the affirmation
of life is is is is optimistic and it is
an embodied precognitive choice I can't
really use the word precognitive because
I'm not educated enough to really talk
about what cognitive means in modern
cognitive science but it looks to me
like something precognitive and I think
in a psychedelic experience we can get
this orientation of how to navigate
before things become too fixed right we
meet anomaly and we can think of jordan
Peterson's chaos in order to help grasp
this concept of it anomaly is what
happens when you're out there in chaos
it's a moment you can call it an
encounter right and then you have a
decision as to how you respond to that
and there's there would be many brake
offs you know of how we can then talk
about that but fundamentally it's pay
attention to it or not and there are
positive and negative senses of both but
anyway you know it is a it is for me for
me these are ideas that are all linked
to what we're seeing and fundamentally
as well it's about it's an instance of a
sort of oppositional nature we we've air
out in ourselves and we see play out in
the world of course you have left them
right you have the internal the AB the X
I know you have materialism and whatever
else you want to say you know and it is
that it is that appropriate
harmonization of opposites to dissolve
them but to coagulate them again to
bring them together again right it's not
about taking away the polarities it's
about it's about engaging in the kind of
individual action as it meets the
collective that appropriately Orient's
right that oppositional motivation and
reconstitutes it so it's so it's
properly harmonized for whatever is but
you know adaptive for the time but
that's so abstract what does that mean
you know to embody it and talk to people
and engage with these ideas that's why
we see it come out in gender and
what-have-you but because it's such a
you know people can grapple on to these
sorts of things a little bit and that's
a conversation I do want to have but I'm
not educated to have to the standard
that I think is required if you
ultimately want to try and lead people
through with such a ridiculous chaotic
time but I see it's something you're
taking on and I really admire that I
think it takes a lot of bravery I think
what you're doing it takes a lot of
bravery and vulnerability and I I do see
that and you know the reason why I
contacted you was because I won I
thought you'd say yes and partly because
well I just had a sense that the time
was right but also you know because
because uh because uh you would be ready
to have a conversation I see it with
what you're doing so
yeah I don't know what would you like to
talk about would you like to talk about
your men's work I mean because that if
that is somewhere where you have from my
limited understanding sort of
demonstrable expertise in leading a
group of men to engage with some of
these aspects of themselves so this is
one way you know in a you know in a
communal way we can bring people
together and start to deal with
fundamentally what's what's confusing
about ourselves when we look in and you
can call that the shadow and then below
that you have the animal unless if you
want to be young in about it and you
have various complexes of the personal
unconscious as well and it's so so
complicated but how do you conceptualize
what you're doing there and you know
what do you want to how do you want to
build that into to rebel wisdom so we
were starting the men's work kind of at
the same time as the media stuff it was
sort of a coincidence that I happen to
be being mentored via a guy who's been
doing this work since the 70s and I
think I mean I see it in a continuum
because what we need to do is to really
ground ourselves in ourselves that's
where we need to go as well right now
and that for me involves there's
something that happens when men are with
men and women are with women that is a
really essential grounding and AB in a
sort of deeper being a polarity that
then it gives us fuel mm-hmm and we talk
about vitamin M on our workshops the
idea that there's something that we're
craving I think it's a deep evolutionary
history of men with men with men and
there is something that everyone there
feels on a really deep level when when
they're in that space and there's also
something that when we really focus our
intention on what's working in our lives
what isn't working in our lives and
bring that level of intensity to it
change can happen we need to I think in
our lives we need to kind of almost
artificially create that or artificially
but we need to create that for ourselves
and that's what everyone who comes to
the workshops is bringing there's a kind
of real and we we kind of encourage them
to bring that
level of intensity it's like okay what
are you what do you really want to
happen in your life what do you really
want to change and it's only with that
level of intensity and that level of
recognition and support that I think we
can make those changes it's very hard in
our everyday lives without sort of
carving out a space for it and we also
say we have to do it ourselves we don't
have to do it alone so there's a sense
of sort of community and support and
really willing each other to become the
best we can be and that is something I
think yeah I think men with other men
find it a lot easier to give that than
when women are present because when
women are present there often comes in a
bit of performance a bit of anxiety a
bit of sort of showing off in front of
the other man there's a there's
something that comes in that that is is
a different element into that field
interesting and it's not wrong we can
have a really sure there's a lot of yeah
there's a different energy to a mixed
group absolutely but there is something
that being with men allows us to really
support each other and focus and and
recharge ourselves for our relationships
or for Rhian gauging with with with
women in the outside world or you know
just just really yeah it's it's an
essential piece and I think it's an
essential piece for now because of the
chaos of the times we have to ground
ourselves in ourselves I think as men
that means grounding ourselves as men as
well as as people because we have a
biological existence we have any we have
a an embodied existence absolutely and a
lot of men I know from my generation
have a sense of sort of shame around
themselves as men and there's a lot of
that in a culture and I think a lot of
men have internalized themselves that
about themselves and nothing good comes
from shame it's not an empowered space
to be it's it's essential for us to kind
of recognize the way that men have
misbehaved in the past
but it's not for us to take on if it's
not ours
and it's to say I take what's mine
mm-hmm I reject what's not mine that's
being put onto me
and I I yeah I I become the best that I
can be because I think yeah ultimately
we're all being challenged to evolve
that's what the times are calling for
right now we're all gonna have to evolve
and it's never easy all change is never
easy but take it on willingly or it'll
happen to you anyway and it won't be so
much fun
yeah yeah I think that is the right
message David thank you very much for
talking to me if anybody wants to get in
touch with what I'm doing they can check
out voice of calm voice car videos on
YouTube it's something similar at least
it's motivated I think by by that app
willingness to take responsibility for
the right way to face change was a lot
of ways you can put it but thank you so
much for taking the time it's really
beautiful Akito thank you
[Music]